(Watch on www.kisskh.li Support Admin)
(Ver en www.kisskh.li Apoyo al administrador)
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
THIS IS A WORK OF FICTION
ESTA ES UNA OBRA DE FICCIÓN
CHILD ACTORS AND ANIMALS WERE FILMED SAFELY
LOS NIÑOS ACTORES Y LOS ANIMALES FUERON FILMADOS DE FORMA SEGURA.
The unyielding throne of Joseon
El trono inquebrantable de Joseon
stood firm for 600 years…
Se mantuvo firme durante 600 años…
before fading under the constitutional monarchy.
antes de desvanecerse bajo la monarquía constitucional.
Though its prestige endured, it became largely ceremonial.
Aunque su prestigio perduró, se convirtió en gran medida en un acto ceremonial.
Power became class.
El poder se convirtió en clase.
Class became hereditary.
La clase social se volvió hereditaria.
And it held on…
Y se mantuvo...
tenaciously.
con tenacidad.
Make way, make way.
¡Abran paso, abran paso!
I said, move.
Dije, muévete.
2009 ROYAL ACADEMY SPRING EXAM RANKING
CLASIFICACIÓN DE LOS EXÁMENES DE PRIMAVERA DE LA REAL ACADEMIA DE 2009
SEONG HUIJU, JUJAK HOUSE
SEONG HUIJU, CASA JUJAK
SECOND- RYU MINSEOK, CHEONGNYONG HOUSE
SEGUNDO - RYU MINSEOK, CASA CHEONGNYONG
It's that brat again?
¿Es ese mocoso otra vez?
You said you'd win.
Dijiste que ganarías.
And yet you lost again.
Y sin embargo, volviste a perder.
Only fools flail desperately over trifles.
Solo los tontos se agitan desesperadamente por nimiedades.
Aren't you exhausted yet?
¿Todavía no estás agotado?
Hmm?
¿Mmm?
Was it hard for you?
¿Te resultó difícil?
I didn't find this exam difficult at all.
Este examen no me resultó difícil en absoluto.
You've lost. Learn to accept defeat.
Has perdido. Aprende a aceptar la derrota.
Don't run your mouth and embarrass yourself.
No hables de más y hagas el ridículo.
You're not even a noble.
Ni siquiera eres un noble.
Know your place.
Conoce tu lugar.
Watch your mouth, you noble prick.
Cuida tu boca, noble imbécil.
Do you want to be written up?
¿Quieres que escribamos sobre ti?
Damn it.
Maldita sea.
You should put some effort into it next time, Minseok.
Deberías esforzarte un poco más la próxima vez, Minseok.
Okay?
¿Bueno?
How is it you lose every single time?
¿Cómo es que pierdes siempre?
You're an esteemed nobleman, after all.
Después de todo, usted es un noble muy respetado.
Just look at this mess of a uniform.
¡Miren este desastre de uniforme!
Is Huiju the top laureate for the ninth grade again?
¿Huiju es de nuevo la mejor alumna de noveno grado?
Yes, sir.
Sí, señor.
The morale in Jujak House must be through the roof.
La moral en Jujak House debe estar por las nubes.
Everyone's spirits are high.
El ánimo de todos está por las nubes.
Seong Huiju.
Seong Huiju.
-Yes? -Are you aware of our founding philosophy?
-¿Sí? -¿Conoce nuestra filosofía fundacional?
-Pardon? -Why the Crown established this school.
-¿Perdón? -¿Por qué la Corona fundó esta escuela?
Well…
Bien…
Equal opportunity and…
Igualdad de oportunidades y…
That's right. Equal opportunity was very much the objective.
Así es. La igualdad de oportunidades era, sin duda, el objetivo principal.
Seonggyungwan is great and all,
Seonggyungwan es genial y todo eso,
but limiting admission to noblemen's sons has obvious limits.
Pero limitar la admisión a los hijos de los nobles tiene limitaciones obvias.
Right.
Bien.
Do you know who invented this?
¿Sabes quién inventó esto?
That's right.
Así es.
A masterpiece of its era, commissioned by King Sejong
Una obra maestra de su época, encargada por el rey Sejong.
and crafted by Jang Yeongsil.
y elaborada por Jang Yeongsil.
Isn't it?
¿No es así?
He may have been the son of a courtesan,
Puede que fuera hijo de una cortesana,
but he had a brilliant mind.
pero tenía una mente brillante.
Here. Take this.
Toma. Toma esto.
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
EPISODE 1
EPISODIO 1
You said we'd win,
Dijiste que ganaríamos,
but we lost.
pero perdimos.
Lost?
¿Perdido?
We remain the industry leader,
Seguimos siendo líderes del sector,
and we also ranked first in the preference survey.
y también quedamos en primer lugar en la encuesta de preferencias.
You know how underhanded their promotional tactics can be.
Ya sabes lo deshonestas que pueden ser sus tácticas promocionales.
They're offering 50% off as part of their launch event.
Ofrecen un 50% de descuento como parte de su evento de lanzamiento.
And you know Lee Yungyeong, who made a comeback?
¿Y conoces a Lee Yungyeong, que ha vuelto a la música?
They managed to create some buzz with that celebrity endorsement.
Consiguieron generar bastante expectación gracias al respaldo de esa celebridad.
So,
Entonces,
you're confirming we lost
Estás confirmando que perdimos
in terms of sales.
en términos de ventas.
My apologies, ma'am.
Mis disculpas, señora.
Let's start digging.
Empecemos a excavar.
Who shall we dig into exactly?
¿En quién vamos a indagar exactamente?
Don't tell me you want us to dig into their CEO.
No me digas que quieres que investiguemos a su director ejecutivo.
That's asking for trouble.
Eso es buscarse problemas.
That would be a complete waste of time.
Eso sería una completa pérdida de tiempo.
Of course.
Por supuesto.
Lee Yungyeong turned us down and became their spokesperson.
Lee Yungyeong nos rechazó y se convirtió en su portavoz.
Dig into her.
Profundiza en ella.
Understood. Pardon?
Entendido. ¿Perdón?
When a single ad blows up like this, there are bound to be issues.
Cuando un solo anuncio se vuelve viral de esta manera, es inevitable que surjan problemas.
Where there are issues, trouble follows.
Donde hay problemas, surgen dificultades.
It shouldn't be too difficult to spin them into a full-blown media storm.
No debería ser demasiado difícil convertirlas en una auténtica tormenta mediática.
No… …it shouldn't be difficult, but…
No… …no debería ser difícil, pero…
If it's not difficult, then do it.
Si no es difícil, entonces hazlo.
Play dirty and cheap.
Juega sucio y barato.
-Yes, ma'am. -Logistics.
-Sí, señora. -Logística.
Yes, ma'am.
Sí, señora.
I'm the logistics manager.
Soy el gerente de logística.
What?
¿Qué?
You two could be twins.
Ustedes dos podrían ser gemelos.
Anyhow, let's cut outbound volume.
En cualquier caso, reduzcamos el volumen de llamadas salientes.
-By half. -That much?
-Por la mitad. -¿Tanto?
Spark fear of missing out in consumers and push the products to sell out.
Generar en los consumidores el temor a perderse algo y presionar para que los productos se agoten.
Make it go viral.
Haz que se vuelva viral.
As quickly and loudly as possible.
Lo más rápido y fuerte posible.
-Yes, ma'am. -Wait, hold on.
-Sí, señora. -Espere, un momento.
That's not as easy as it sounds. The units have already been produced.
No es tan fácil como parece. Las unidades ya han sido fabricadas.
-Toss them. -Pardon?
-Tíralos. -¿Perdón?
Bury them or burn them.
Entiérralos o quémalos.
The possibilities are endless.
Las posibilidades son infinitas.
But we'd take a huge loss…
Pero sufriríamos una pérdida enorme…
Gosh, look at our logistics manager.
Vaya, miren a nuestro gerente de logística.
Sounds like you save every penny just to pinch it harder.
Parece que ahorras cada centavo solo para luego escatimar aún más.
Yeah. My goodness.
Sí. Dios mío.
I hope all that saving makes you ridiculously rich.
Espero que todos esos ahorros te hagan increíblemente rico.
I will decide
Yo decidiré
what I do with my money.
lo que hago con mi dinero.
-Whose phone is that? -Unbelievable.
-¿De quién es ese teléfono? -Increíble.
That's five minutes. We're done.
Son cinco minutos. Hemos terminado.
Hold on. We have one more item.
Un momento. Nos queda un artículo más.
Traffic downtown is already nuts. You don't want to be late.
El tráfico en el centro ya es una locura. No querrás llegar tarde.
I get it!
¡Lo entiendo!
Why did His Majesty have to be born today of all days?
¿Por qué tuvo que nacer Su Majestad precisamente hoy?
You all know I'll be at the palace today.
Todos sabéis que estaré hoy en el palacio.
I'll be drumming up some serious buzz for us.
Voy a generar mucha expectación a nuestro favor.
So I expect all of you
Así que espero que todos ustedes
to work just as hard.
trabajar igual de duro.
-Yes, ma'am. -Of course.
—Sí, señora. —Por supuesto.
What exactly should we--
¿Qué deberíamos hacer exactamente?
Write up articles. Articles.
Redactar artículos. Artículos.
-Articles. -Yes. Articles.
-Artículos. -Sí. Artículos.
Articles…
Artículos…
"Castle Group successor gets invited to His Majesty's Royal Birthday Banquet."
"El sucesor de Castle Group es invitado al banquete de cumpleaños real de Su Majestad."
Killer headline, don't you think?
Un titular impactante, ¿no crees?
You're the successor now?
¿Ahora eres el sucesor?
-No. -Then why did you lie?
-No. -Entonces, ¿por qué mentiste?
The ones who claim they're all that rarely are.
Quienes afirman serlo todo rara vez lo son.
They all say it, hoping to will it into existence.
Todos lo dicen, con la esperanza de que se haga realidad.
Do you know nothing about PR?
¿No sabes nada de relaciones públicas?
THE ROYAL FAMILY GATHERS FOR THE KING'S ROYAL BIRTHDAY
LA FAMILIA REAL SE REÚNE PARA EL CUMPLEAÑOS REAL DEL REY
…PREPARES FOR A ROYAL CELEBRATION…
…SE PREPARA PARA UNA CELEBRACIÓN REAL…
ROYAL BIRTHDAY BANQUET AT GYEONGBOKGUNG PALACE…
BANQUETE REAL DE CUMPLEAÑOS EN EL PALACIO DE GYEONGBOKGUNG…
Your Royal Highness, you must make haste.
Su Alteza Real, debe darse prisa.
-Your Royal Highness! -Excuse me.
-¡Su Alteza Real! -Disculpe.
I'll handle it from here. You all can go.
Yo me encargo de aquí en adelante. Ya pueden irse.
Your Royal Highness, it is Hyeon.
Su Alteza Real, soy Hyeon.
Come in.
Adelante.
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Have you prepared a gift?
¿Has preparado un regalo?
After seeing blood all morning…
Después de ver sangre toda la mañana…
…I remain fervid.
…Sigo ferviente.
Fervid, I see.
Ferviente, veo.
-Shall I get you some tea? -No.
-¿Te preparo un té? -No.
-I need to catch up on sleep. -Wait.
-Necesito recuperar el sueño. -Espera.
Your Royal Highness,
Su Alteza Real,
as if hunting today were not bad enough, now you wish to take a nap?
Como si la caza de hoy no hubiera sido ya bastante mala, ¿ahora quieres echarte una siesta?
That will not do.
Eso no servirá.
-I mean, out of all days-- -Choi Hyeon.
-Quiero decir, de entre todos los días... -Choi Hyeon.
Aide Choi Hyeon.
Ayuda a Choi Hyeon.
But today is His Majesty's Royal Birthday Banquet!
¡Pero hoy es el banquete de cumpleaños real de Su Majestad!
Please wave this way!
¡Por favor, salude hacia aquí!
-Look over here! -Please look over here!
-¡Mira aquí! -¡Por favor, mira aquí!
I'm currently standing outside the palace,
Actualmente estoy parado afuera del palacio,
where the Royal Birthday Banquet is being held.
donde se celebra el banquete de cumpleaños real .
Distinguished guests of the royal family
Distinguidos invitados de la familia real
are arriving one after another.
están llegando uno tras otro.
Ms. Seong, please look over here!
¡Señorita Seong, por favor mire aquí!
Did Seong Huiju really wear red to come to the palace?
¿De verdad Seong Huiju vistió de rojo para ir al palacio?
You know she's a clout chaser.
Ya sabes que busca fama a toda costa.
Can't deny she's beautiful.
No se puede negar que es hermosa.
-Go on. Take pictures. -All right.
—Adelante. Toma fotos. —De acuerdo.
Get to work.
Empezar a trabajar.
All right! Ms. Seong has grabbed their attention.
¡Muy bien! La señorita Seong ha captado su atención.
What do we do now?
¿Qué hacemos ahora?
Now we begin!
¡Ahora comenzamos!
Go on! Get to it! Hurry up!
¡Vamos! ¡Manos a la obra! ¡Date prisa!
We must sell out of everything she's wearing!
¡ Tenemos que vender todo lo que lleva puesto!
Type faster!
¡Escribe más rápido!
Find all the photos and articles she's featured in.
Encuentra todas las fotos y artículos en los que aparece.
You will find them if you look.
Los encontrarás si buscas.
You must keep searching, and you must type faster.
Debes seguir buscando y debes escribir más rápido.
That's the spirit! We can do this, people!
¡Ese es el espíritu! ¡Podemos hacerlo, gente!
We are Castle Group!
¡Somos Castle Group!
SEONG HUIJU'S RED SUIT STEALS THE SPOTLIGHT
EL TRAJE ROJO DE SEONG HUIJU ACAPARÁ TODAS LAS MOLESTIAS
RETHINKING RED SUITS NOW…
REPENSANDO LOS TRAJES ROJOS AHORA…
…SOLD OUT ALREADY…
…AGOTADO…
THE CUT OF THAT SUIT IS INSANE!
¡EL CORTE DE ESE TRAJE ES INCREÍBLE!
Seong Huiju's suit! Seong Huiju's bag!
¡El traje de Seong Huiju! ¡El bolso de Seong Huiju!
Seong Huiju's shoes!
¡Los zapatos de Seong Huiju!
That's so pretty.
Es muy bonito.
Those are just too cute. I can't even.
Son demasiado lindos. No puedo creerlo.
Sold out!
¡Agotado!
SHE WEARS IT, IT SELLS OUT
ELLA LO USA, SE AGOTA
"Castle Group successor gets invited
"El sucesor de Castle Group recibe una invitación"
to His Majesty's Royal Birthday Banquet."
al banquete de cumpleaños real de Su Majestad."
Have you been well?
¿Has estado bien?
That's her, right?
Esa es ella, ¿verdad?
-The second child of Castle Group? -Second? As if.
-¿El segundo hijo del Grupo Castillo? -¿Segundo? ¡Ni hablar!
They didn't even know she existed until she was ten.
Ni siquiera sabían de su existencia hasta que cumplió diez años.
What do you mean?
¿Qué quieres decir?
The mistress raised her,
La señora la crió,
and when she was about ten,
y cuando tenía unos diez años,
she was sent to Chairman Seong.
Fue enviada ante el presidente Seong.
A commoner, born out of wedlock, no less?
¿Una plebeya, nacida fuera del matrimonio, nada menos?
Yeah.
Sí.
That would explain her various shortcomings.
Eso explicaría sus diversas deficiencias.
No sense of honor or dignity.
Carecen de sentido del honor y la dignidad.
Obnoxious and without a shred of sense.
Detestable y sin pizca de sentido común.
So on and so forth.
Y así sucesivamente.
In short, she's a psycho?
En resumen, ¿es una psicópata?
Cheers.
Salud.
Wow, is that CEO Seong, the industry's runner-up?
Vaya, ¿ese es el director ejecutivo Seong, el subcampeón de la industria?
Excuse me. I'll take one of those.
Disculpe. Tomaré uno de esos.
Thank you.
Gracias.
I know you can hear me.
Sé que puedes oírme.
Then hear this. Get lost.
Entonces escucha esto. Piérdete.
Show some respect to your brother.
Demuéstrale algo de respeto a tu hermano.
This is why people call you uncultured.
Por eso la gente te llama inculto.
I thought you at least possessed some business prowess, but…
Pensaba que al menos tenías cierta habilidad para los negocios, pero…
I heard your sales slipped recently.
He oído que sus ventas han bajado últimamente.
I just don't understand it.
Simplemente no lo entiendo.
Rumors have spread far and wide.
Los rumores se han extendido por todas partes.
I know.
Lo sé.
Far and wide, right?
Por todas partes, ¿verdad?
We don't have any flashy ad campaigns.
No tenemos campañas publicitarias llamativas.
No discounts, either.
Tampoco hay descuentos.
Despite all your stunts like the ad campaign, virality,
A pesar de todas tus acrobacias como la campaña publicitaria, la viralidad,
and even the half-off sales event, my brand still took
e incluso el evento de ventas con un 50% de descuento, mi marca aún tomó
the top spot in the preference survey, surpassing yours.
el primer puesto en la encuesta de preferencias, superando al tuyo.
Common knowledge, apparently.
Al parecer, es de conocimiento general.
I'm concerned about pushback on the high price point.
Me preocupa la posible reacción negativa ante el precio elevado.
But cutting prices would just kill me.
Pero bajar los precios me mataría.
It feels so bargain-bin.
Parece un artículo de saldo.
Just like somebody.
Igual que alguien.
What, "Bargain-bin"?
¿Qué, "liquidación"?
Unbelievable.
Increíble.
Hey, that's just your inferiority complex talking.
Oye, eso es solo tu complejo de inferioridad hablando.
My… …inferiority complex?
¿Mi… …complejo de inferioridad?
-Me? -Yeah.
-¿Yo? -Sí.
-Triggered by you?
-¿Te has enfadado por ti?
You're clearly obsessed with luxury marketing
Está claro que te obsesiona el marketing de lujo.
because deep inside, you're a knockoff.
Porque en el fondo, eres una imitación.
I get you're trying hard to cover up your lowly origins,
Entiendo que estás tratando de ocultar tus humildes orígenes,
but please just try to live a life benefiting your station.
Pero por favor, intenten vivir una vida que beneficie a su emisora.
Stop glaring, you brat.
Deja de mirarme así, mocoso.
I'm your older brother.
Soy tu hermano mayor.
I just hate seeing you like that as your older brother.
Como tu hermano mayor, simplemente odio verte así .
Maybe we're only half, but at the end of the day,
Tal vez solo seamos la mitad, pero al final del día,
we're still siblings.
Seguimos siendo hermanos.
Hmm? Right?
¿Hmm? ¿Verdad?
Yapping away like a little lapdog.
Parloteando como un perrito faldero.
What? Why you--
¿Qué? ¿Por qué tú...?
If you're going to yap like that, at least wear a leash.
Si vas a hablar así, al menos lleva una correa.
A leash I could pull to choke you with.
Una correa que podría usar para estrangularte.
Also, it's "a life befitting your station,"
Además, es "una vida acorde a tu posición".
not "a life benefiting your station," you moron.
No es "una vida que beneficie tu posición", imbécil.
We will now make our way to Junghwajeon Hall.
Ahora nos dirigiremos al Salón Junghwajeon.
We're a package deal here.
Aquí somos un paquete completo.
Just two-bit peddlers.
Simples vendedores ambulantes de poca monta.
I can't see anything from back here.
No puedo ver nada desde aquí atrás.
That pillar isn't helping.
Ese pilar no ayuda.
Oh, boy.
Oh, vaya.
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Why aren't they starting?
¿Por qué no empiezan?
Grand Prince I-AN isn't here yet.
El Gran Príncipe I-AN aún no ha llegado.
What's taking him so long?
¿Por qué tarda tanto?
Announcing Grand Prince I-AN.
Presentamos al Gran Príncipe I-AN.
Hey, look at what he's wearing.
Oye, mira lo que lleva puesto.
Is he here for a hunt?
¿Está aquí para cazar?
Shut it.
Cállate.
My apologies, Your Majesty.
Mis disculpas, Su Majestad.
Queen Mother Yun.
Reina Madre Yun.
Uncle!
¡Tío!
Please accept my warmest wishes.
Reciba mis más cordiales deseos.
What manner of attire is this?
¿Qué tipo de vestimenta es esta?
His Majesty bestowed this silk upon me some time ago.
Su Majestad me obsequió esta seda hace algún tiempo.
Is it not to your liking?
¿No es de tu agrado?
It looks so good on you--
Te queda muy bien.
You must observe decorum.
Debes observar el decoro.
Hunting season has passed.
La temporada de caza ha terminado.
Do you believe hunting is limited to a season?
¿Crees que la caza está limitada a una temporada?
You can lecture me later.
Puedes darme una charla más tarde.
I must take my seat…
Debo tomar asiento…
for all of them to take theirs.
para que todos tomen el suyo.
The nation has been celebrating
La nación ha estado celebrando
in honor of His Majesty's royal birthday.
en honor al cumpleaños real de Su Majestad.
Events at Cheonggyecheon Stream and Gwanghwamun
Eventos en Cheonggyecheon Stream y Gwanghwamun
are set to carry on throughout the night.
Está previsto que continúen durante toda la noche.
With the day designated a public holiday, heavy traffic is expected
Al ser día festivo, se espera un tráfico intenso.
as crowds head out for the break.
mientras la multitud se dirige al descanso.
Following the ceremony featuring the formal greetings,
Tras la ceremonia en la que se pronunciaron los saludos formales,
the second half will begin alongside a Nakhwa Nori display.
La segunda parte comenzará con una exhibición del Nakhwa Nori.
After His Majesty writes down a wish and presents it to Grand Prince I-AN,
Después de que Su Majestad escriba un deseo y se lo presente al Gran Príncipe I-AN,
His Royal Highness will commence the Nakhwa Nori.
Su Alteza Real dará comienzo al Nakhwa Nori.
Good health for Queen Mother.
Que la Reina Madre goce de buena salud.
Good health for Uncle.
Que Dios te bendiga, tío.
Happiness for the people.
Felicidad para la gente.
Well done, Your Majesty.
Bien hecho, Su Majestad.
-Hello, Prime Minister Min. -It's nice to see you, sir.
-Hola, Primer Ministro. -Es un placer verlo, señor.
-Hello there. -I'm always rooting for you.
-Hola. -Siempre te apoyo.
Thank you for all your hard work.
Gracias por todo vuestro esfuerzo.
-It's nice to see you. -So handsome.
-Es un placer verte. -Qué guapo.
My goodness.
Dios mío.
Seong Huiju.
Seong Huiju.
Ooh.
Oh.
-Should I call you Prime Minister Min? -Come on now.
-¿Debo llamarte Primer Ministro Min? -Vamos.
Don't. That'd be so awkward.
No lo hagas. Sería muy incómodo.
Look at that rosy pink floral overcoat.
Mira ese abrigo rosa con estampado floral.
You didn't come to play.
No viniste a jugar.
The Cabinet would bite my head off if I showed up here in civilian clothes.
El Gabinete me regañaría si apareciera aquí vestido de civil.
Where were you? I couldn't find you earlier.
¿Dónde estabas? No te encontré antes.
I was all the way in the back.
Yo estaba al fondo del todo.
And you must've been in the front row.
Y seguro que estabas en primera fila.
How's the front row? Is it fun?
¿Qué tal la primera fila? ¿Es divertida?
Don't get me started. It was so boring I almost fell asleep.
Ni me lo menciones. Fue tan aburrido que casi me quedo dormido.
It was pure torture.
Fue una auténtica tortura.
-You've been crushing it. -Me?
-Lo has estado haciendo genial. -¿Yo?
I hear Castle Beauty's US rollout is going well.
He oído que el lanzamiento de Castle Beauty en Estados Unidos está yendo bien.
Hmm.
Mmm.
I'm sure everyone is secretly shocked.
Estoy seguro de que todos están secretamente sorprendidos.
Taeju tried and failed at the same venture two years ago.
Taeju lo intentó hace dos años en la misma empresa, pero fracasó.
Come on.
Vamos.
You know I'm in a different league than him.
Sabes que estoy en otra liga que él.
But… was this outfit intentional?
Pero… ¿este atuendo fue intencional?
Yeah.
Sí.
Why? You don't like it?
¿Por qué? ¿No te gusta?
I thought red wasn't permitted in the palace.
Creía que el rojo no estaba permitido en el palacio.
Who cares? It's not like I'm breaking any laws.
¿A quién le importa? No estoy infringiendo ninguna ley.
You should still be careful. It could lead to controversy.
Aun así, debes tener cuidado. Podría generar controversia.
What's so bad about a little controversy?
¿Qué tiene de malo un poco de controversia?
Nobody knows who Seong Taeju is,
Nadie sabe quién es Seong Taeju,
but everyone knows Seong Huiju.
Pero todo el mundo conoce a Seong Huiju.
They know I'm the CEO of Castle Beauty
Saben que soy el director ejecutivo de Castle Beauty.
and that I'm an illegitimate child.
y que soy un hijo ilegítimo.
Hey.
Ey.
Prime Minister Min.
Primer Ministro Ministro.
I need to go.
Tengo que ir.
Make some time for me soon. Let's grab a bite.
Hazme un hueco pronto. Vamos a comer algo.
As long as you don't show up in that.
Siempre y cuando no aparezcas ahí.
That's enough teasing.
Ya basta de bromas.
Bye.
Adiós.
-Prime Minister Min. -Hello.
-Primer Ministro Min. -Hola.
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
How many times have I told you not to run off alone?
¿Cuántas veces te he dicho que no te vayas solo?
Why?
¿Por qué?
Are you afraid I might be assassinated quietly?
¿Temes que puedan asesinarme en silencio?
I'm more worried about your aide dying from stress.
Me preocupa más que tu asistente muera de estrés.
You disappeared, and he came running…
Desapareciste, y él vino corriendo…
You should just be more careful. You're precious cargo.
Deberías tener más cuidado. Eres una carga valiosa.
Why aren't you getting married?
¿Por qué no te casas?
That's random.
Eso es aleatorio.
Half the maidens at the banquet couldn't stop staring at you.
La mitad de las doncellas del banquete no podían dejar de mirarte.
What's this now?
¿Qué es esto ahora?
The other half… No.
La otra mitad… No.
More than half of them were staring at me.
Más de la mitad de ellos me estaban mirando fijamente.
So?
¿Entonces?
You want to marry me off and steal the spotlight?
¿Quieres casarte conmigo y robarme el protagonismo?
Quite the opposite, actually.
Todo lo contrario, en realidad.
Pardon?
¿Indulto?
It appears I'll soon be married.
Parece que pronto me casaré.
You will?
¿Vas a?
My sister-in-law presses me to take a spouse day after day.
Mi cuñada me presiona día tras día para que me case.
It'll happen sooner rather than later.
Sucederá más pronto que tarde.
That will make your life quite difficult.
Eso te hará la vida bastante difícil.
Me?
¿A mí?
I'd have to leave the palace if I got married.
Tendría que abandonar el palacio si me casara.
It'll be difficult to serve as regent from outside the palace.
Será difícil ejercer como regente desde fuera del palacio.
But His Majesty, at the tender age of eight,
Pero Su Majestad, a la tierna edad de ocho años,
cannot attend to state affairs.
no puede atender los asuntos de Estado.
The duties you dumped on me,
Las tareas que me endosaste,
including the various charity events,
incluyendo los diversos eventos benéficos,
hosting of diplomatic delegations,
acogida de delegaciones diplomáticas,
visiting international organizations, cultural heritage management,
Visitar organizaciones internacionales, gestión del patrimonio cultural,
and the unbearably dull military ceremonies
y las ceremonias militares insoportablemente aburridas
will all fall to you once more.
Todo volverá a recaer sobre ti.
What could go wrong?
¿Qué podría salir mal?
That will not do.
Eso no servirá.
No. Absolutely not.
No. Absolutamente no.
That cannot happen.
Eso no puede suceder.
We're already short on royals able to attend to state affairs.
Ya tenemos escasez de miembros de la realeza capaces de atender asuntos de Estado.
If you leave, we won't have--
Si te vas, no tendremos...
-Then block it. -What?
-Entonces bloquéalo. -¿Qué?
Use your veto power.
Usa tu poder de veto.
A royal marriage requires the approval of the Cabinet.
Un matrimonio real requiere la aprobación del Gabinete.
The Royal Family Act.
La Ley de la Familia Real.
He could've just said that from the start.
Podría haberlo dicho desde el principio.
Did he need to make me sweat?
¿Acaso necesitaba hacerme sudar?
Seriously?
¿En serio?
I can't believe they really cut off cell service for this.
No puedo creer que realmente hayan cortado el servicio de telefonía celular por esto.
Who goes there?
¿Quién va allí?
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Name.
Nombre.
Please forgive me.
Por favor, perdóname.
I seem to have lost my way.
Parece que me he perdido.
Your name.
Su nombre.
It is Seong Huiju.
Es Seong Huiju.
Affiliation.
Afiliación.
I am not a member of the palace staff.
No soy miembro del personal del palacio.
Why is an outsider to the court…
¿Por qué un forastero en el tribunal...?
loitering in an area…
merodear en una zona…
not open to the public?
¿No está abierto al público?
If you're gone in the count of three, I'll overlook it.
Si te vas en tres segundos, lo pasaré por alto.
Really?
¿En realidad?
That much I can do for my junior alum.
Eso es todo lo que puedo hacer por mis compañeros exalumnos.
That makes sense…
Eso tiene sentido…
-Pardon? -One.
-¿Perdón? -Uno.
Two.
Dos.
What was that?
¿Qué fue eso?
You stay here.
Quédate aquí.
Are you unharmed?
¿Estás ileso?
What about His Majesty?
¿Y qué hay de Su Majestad?
Do you once more seek…
¿Buscas de nuevo...?
the life of another sovereign?
¿La vida de otro soberano?
Queen Mother!
¡Reina madre!
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
Are you all right?
¿Estás bien?
Manage the optics.
Gestionar la óptica.
Keep the press under control to prevent any conspiracy theories.
Mantengan a la prensa bajo control para evitar cualquier teoría conspirativa.
Aren't we taking this too lightly?
¿No nos lo estamos tomando demasiado a la ligera?
No need to overthink it.
No hay necesidad de darle demasiadas vueltas.
There were no injuries or fatalities.
No hubo heridos ni fallecidos.
The late King passed away in a fire three years ago.
El difunto rey falleció en un incendio hace tres años.
The monarchy has only recently stabilized.
La monarquía se ha estabilizado recientemente.
And now, another fire?
¿Y ahora, otro incendio?
That won't do at all.
Eso no servirá en absoluto.
It shouldn't be over already.
No debería haber terminado ya.
Why…
Por qué…
Hold on.
Esperar.
Don't tell me you just walked out.
No me digas que simplemente te fuiste.
What?
¿Qué?
Oh.
Oh.
Tell me you didn't just leave to draw attention.
Dime que no te fuiste solo para llamar la atención.
I couldn't even if I tried.
No podría ni aunque lo intentara.
-Why not? -There was an incident.
-¿Por qué no? -Hubo un incidente.
You caused an incident?
¿Provocaste un incidente?
Seriously?
¿En serio?
-There was a fire. -A fire?
—Hubo un incendio. —¿Un incendio?
Wait. A fire?
Espera. ¿Un incendio?
What about the Grand Prince? Is he okay?
¿Y el Gran Príncipe? ¿Está bien?
Ms. Do.
Sra. Do.
Are you a fan of Prince I-AN?
¿Eres fan del Príncipe I-AN?
Me?
¿A mí?
I mean…
Quiero decir…
An explosion has occurred at Junghwajeon Hall.
Se ha producido una explosión en el Junghwajeon Hall.
It occurred during the Royal Birthday Banquet,
Ocurrió durante el banquete del cumpleaños real,
but fortunately, no casualties have been reported.
Pero, afortunadamente, no se han reportado víctimas.
The police and fire department…
La policía y los bomberos…
Is there some bad blood?
¿Hay algún rencor?
What?
¿Qué?
Grand Prince I-AN also attended the Royal Academy of Korea.
El Gran Príncipe I-AN también asistió a la Real Academia de Corea.
I thought you might've been bullied or something.
Pensé que tal vez te habían acosado o algo así.
You're so hostile toward him.
Eres muy hostil hacia él.
Yeah, right.
Sí, claro.
Do I look like someone who would be bullied?
¿Acaso parezco alguien que podría sufrir acoso escolar?
That's true.
Eso es cierto.
Then why do you hate him so much?
Entonces, ¿por qué lo odias tanto?
Just because.
Simplemente porque.
He's obnoxious.
Es insoportable.
Please work. Come on.
Por favor, trabajen. Vamos.
Please.
Por favor.
Who goes there?
¿Quién va allí?
If you've done wrong, you must accept a fair punishment.
Si has obrado mal, debes aceptar un castigo justo.
Don't disgrace yourself by getting caught in flight.
No te avergüences dejándote atrapar en pleno vuelo.
Name.
Nombre.
It's Seong Huiju.
Es Seong Huiju.
Affiliation.
Afiliación.
Jujak House. Ninth grade.
Casa Jujak. Noveno grado.
You know you violated school regulations.
Sabes que has infringido las normas escolares.
I needed more training time. The exhibition match is coming up--
Necesitaba más tiempo de entrenamiento. El partido de exhibición se acerca.
Are you a man of virtue or of profit?
¿Eres un hombre virtuoso o un hombre de lucro?
Students under tenth grade are prohibited
Los estudiantes menores de décimo grado están prohibidos.
from leaving the dormitory after 11 p.m.
Salir del dormitorio después de las 11 p. m.
Violation of this rule results in 20 demerit points.
La violación de esta regla conlleva una penalización de 20 puntos.
Use of facilities outside designated training hours
Uso de las instalaciones fuera del horario de formación establecido
requires prior approval from the principal.
Requiere aprobación previa del director.
Violation of this rule results in 10 demerit points.
La violación de esta regla conlleva una penalización de 10 puntos.
-In total… -And Your Royal Highness?
-En total… -¿Y Su Alteza Real?
You are here too, are you not?
Tú también estás aquí, ¿verdad?
Will you receive demerit points as well?
¿También recibirás puntos de penalización?
I'm here with approval.
Estoy aquí para dar mi aprobación.
ARCHERY RANGE USAGE APPROVAL
AUTORIZACIÓN DE USO EN CAMPO DE TIRO CON ARCO
How'd you get this?
¿Cómo conseguiste esto?
After all that talk about students getting carried away for the exhibition match
Después de toda esa charla sobre los estudiantes que se dejaron llevar por el partido de exhibición
and the archery range not being meant for individual training?
¿Y el campo de tiro con arco no está destinado al entrenamiento individual?
I got this key from Ryu Minseok, Cheongnyong House, ninth grade.
Esta llave me la dio Ryu Minseok, de la casa Cheongnyong, de noveno grado.
-Ryu Minseok? -Yes.
-Ryu Minseok? -Sí.
He was shamelessly bragging about having this key,
Se jactaba descaradamente de tener esa llave,
so I stole it.
Así que lo robé.
I'm not sure why an individual had a key to this archery range
No estoy seguro de por qué una persona tenía una llave de este campo de tiro con arco.
when it's not a place for individual training.
cuando no es un lugar para entrenamiento individual.
But seeing how easily you obtained this approval notice,
Pero viendo lo fácil que le fue obtener este aviso de aprobación,
I guess it was only out of reach for me.
Supongo que solo estaba fuera de mi alcance.
So do not lecture me about demerit points or whatever.
Así que no me des lecciones sobre puntos de penalización ni nada por el estilo.
I intend
Tengo la intención
to enjoy every opportunity
disfrutar de cada oportunidad
my enemy enjoys.
Mi enemigo disfruta.
You wish to stoop to their level?
¿Deseas rebajarte a su nivel?
I'd rather play dirty and win
Prefiero jugar sucio y ganar.
than play clean and lose.
que jugar limpio y perder.
So obnoxious.
Qué desagradable.
Your Royal Highness. The Queen Mother has arrived.
Su Alteza Real. La Reina Madre ha llegado.
Escort her in.
Acompáñala adentro.
IN TIMES OF PEACE, DO NOT FORGET DANGER
EN TIEMPOS DE PAZ, NO OLVIDES EL PELIGRO
IN TIMES OF PROSPERITY, DO NOT FORGET RUIN
EN TIEMPOS DE PROSPERIDAD, NO OLVIDES LA RUINA
IN TIMES OF ORDER, DO NOT FORGET CHAOS
EN TIEMPOS DE ORDEN, NO OLVIDES EL CAOS.
Must I wait longer?
¿Debo esperar más tiempo?
Grand Prince.
Gran Príncipe.
Yes?
¿Sí?
About yesterday…
Sobre ayer…
I regret my actions.
Me arrepiento de mis acciones.
I was not in my right mind.
No estaba en mis cabales.
I feared some misfortune had struck His Majesty.
Temía que alguna desgracia le hubiera ocurrido a Su Majestad.
Prime Minister Min has asked for the details
El primer ministro Min ha solicitado los detalles.
of how the Queen Mother
de cómo la Reina Madre
dared to strike the Grand Prince and lash out with such unspeakable words.
Se atrevió a golpear al Gran Príncipe y a proferirle palabras tan indescriptibles.
So I hear.
Eso es lo que he oído.
Do not worry.
No te preocupes.
I shall tell him you took responsibility
Le diré que asumiste la responsabilidad.
and expressed remorse
y expresó remordimiento
for your actions.
por tus acciones.
No one shows concern for His Majesty.
Nadie muestra preocupación por Su Majestad.
The palace was on fire,
El palacio estaba en llamas,
and the King almost died.
y el rey casi muere.
Yet all anyone seems to care about is the scratch on your cheek.
Sin embargo, a todo el mundo parece importarle únicamente el rasguño en tu mejilla.
Am I to blame for that?
¿Tengo yo la culpa de eso?
Yes, you are. You are the regent.
Sí, lo eres. Eres el regente.
His Majesty is a mere eight years of age.
Su Majestad tiene tan solo ocho años.
Far too young to be overseeing state affairs.
Demasiado joven para estar al frente de los asuntos de Estado.
So my regency is unavoidable.
Así que mi regencia es inevitable.
-I-AN… -Furthermore,
-Yo-un… -Además,
a regent holds no special powers.
Un regente no tiene poderes especiales.
-I-AN! -Politicians…
-¡Yo-an! -Políticos…
engage in politics.
participar en política.
Peddlers engage in business.
Los vendedores ambulantes se dedican al comercio.
The monarchy remains passive.
La monarquía permanece pasiva.
Simply doing nothing…
Simplemente no hacer nada…
is its sole duty.
es su único deber.
Have you ever considered that to be true power?
¿Alguna vez has considerado que eso sea verdadero poder?
The politicians
Los políticos
burn with fervor to claim a place at your side.
Arderán de fervor por reclamar un lugar a tu lado.
Because a single photo taken beside you
Porque una sola foto tomada a tu lado
wields greater power than ten pledges wrought with painstaking care.
Tiene mayor poder que diez promesas elaboradas con esmero.
And the business elites?
¿Y las élites empresariales?
They hasten to attend to you on every diplomatic tour.
Se apresuran a atenderle en cada gira diplomática.
The mere fact that you granted them a place by your side
El mero hecho de que les hayas concedido un lugar a tu lado
is enough to gain the trust of their investors.
Es suficiente para ganarse la confianza de sus inversores.
You eclipse…
Tú eclipsas…
the Crown itself.
la Corona misma.
Father.
Padre.
I have received a 100 on my exam.
He obtenido un 100 en mi examen.
-Rise above such trifles. -Sorry?
-Eleva tu mirada por encima de esas nimiedades. -¿Perdón?
If it be remarkable, it is but the natural order.
Si resulta sorprendente, no es más que el orden natural de las cosas.
If it be lacking,
Si falta,
it is but a cause for shame.
No es más que motivo de vergüenza.
But Father,
Pero Padre,
is diligence not the duty of a man of virtue?
¿Acaso la diligencia no es el deber de un hombre virtuoso?
You are a Grand Prince before you are a man of virtue.
Eres un Gran Príncipe antes que un hombre virtuoso.
I-SHIN
I-SHIN
That is your new royal title.
Ese es tu nuevo título real.
My royal title is to change?
¿Mi título real va a cambiar?
It is a reminder to remain true and just.
Es un recordatorio para permanecer fieles a nosotros mismos y ser justos.
Do not stand in the way of the Crown Prince.
No se interpongan en el camino del Príncipe Heredero.
This is your new royal title.
Este es tu nuevo título real.
I-AN
Yo-AN
Am I being…
¿Estoy siendo...?
rewarded again?
¿Recompensado de nuevo?
And so…
Y entonces…
what do you seek from me?
¿Qué esperas de mí?
That you be His Majesty's steadfast pillar of support.
Que seas el pilar inquebrantable de apoyo de Su Majestad.
I already serve in that capacity.
Ya desempeño ese cargo.
Proceed to your nuptials.
Procedan a su boda.
Wed the woman of my choosing
Casarme con la mujer que yo elija
and demonstrate your allegiance to His Majesty and me.
y demuestren su lealtad a Su Majestad y a mí.
I told you I don't want to.
Ya te dije que no quiero.
Fine.
Bien.
Let's say I concede to everything, and I do get married.
Digamos que cedo en todo y me caso.
I am still an heir to a conglomerate, so strategic M&amp;A is certainly important.
Sigo siendo heredero de un conglomerado, por lo que las fusiones y adquisiciones estratégicas son sin duda importantes.
That's my role in fortifying the family's legacy.
Ese es mi papel a la hora de fortalecer el legado familiar.
But the CEO of a mere subsidiary simply will not do.
Pero el director ejecutivo de una simple filial no sirve.
Do you think that makes any sense?
¿Crees que eso tiene algún sentido?
I'm Seong Huiju!
¡Soy Seong Huiju!
So what if you are?
¿Y qué si lo eres?
Father, we're here.
Padre, ya estamos aquí.
Hey.
Ey.
Must you be so loud?
¿Tienes que hacer tanto ruido?
All you do is bark day and night.
Lo único que haces es ladrar día y noche.
Hello, Father. Huiju.
Hola, Padre. Huiju.
Honey, you want a cup?
Cariño, ¿quieres una taza?
-So hot! -You should be more careful, honey.
-¡Qué calor! -Deberías tener más cuidado, cariño.
You could've warned me.
Podrías haberme avisado.
Don't pester Father too much, Huiju.
No molestes demasiado a papá, Huiju.
He went to great lengths
Se esforzó mucho
to find a proper suitor for you.
para encontrar un pretendiente adecuado para ti.
So you two collaborated on this?
¿Así que ustedes dos colaboraron en esto?
And this is the result?
¿Y este es el resultado?
A nobody who doesn't even make the industry rankings?
¿Un don nadie que ni siquiera aparece en los rankings de la industria?
Shall I use him as a trophy boyfriend?
¿Debería usarlo como novio trofeo?
Why you little…
¿Por qué tú pequeño…?
Our hands are tied.
Tenemos las manos atadas.
When it comes to arranged marriages,
Cuando se trata de matrimonios concertados,
most families tend to nitpick every detail.
La mayoría de las familias tienden a fijarse en cada detalle.
"Every detail"?
"¿Cada detalle"?
So you also nitpicked "every detail" and ended up with this loser?
¿Así que tú también te fijaste en "cada detalle" y terminaste con este perdedor?
That's strange.
Eso es extraño.
With all that nitpicking, you had to see the marriage was doomed.
Con tantas críticas, era evidente que el matrimonio estaba condenado al fracaso.
-Hey, we married for love! -Who cares what the in-laws' pet thinks?
-¡Oye, nos casamos por amor! -¿A quién le importa lo que piense la mascota de los suegros?
-What was that? -That's enough!
-¿Qué fue eso? -¡Ya basta!
She's just impossible.
Es simplemente imposible.
As you said, you'll eventually have to marry.
Como dijiste, tarde o temprano tendrás que casarte.
Who said I didn't want to marry?
¿Quién dijo que no quería casarme?
I just don't want to marry someone that far beneath me.
Simplemente no quiero casarme con alguien tan inferior a mí.
Father, just be honest with me.
Padre, sé sincero conmigo.
You want to take this chance to get rid of me, no?
Quieres aprovechar esta oportunidad para deshacerte de mí, ¿verdad?
Because based on pure competence, that jerk wouldn't stand a chance.
Porque, basándonos en la mera competencia, ese imbécil no tendría ninguna posibilidad.
Hey, who wouldn't stand a chance?
Oye, ¿quién no tendría una oportunidad?
You, obviously. Certainly not me!
Tú, obviamente. ¡Yo desde luego que no!
I guess branding me illegitimate
Supongo que me tachan de ilegítimo
and saddling me with a useless brother wasn't enough?
¿Y encima tener que cargar con un hermano inútil no era suficiente?
Now you want to foist an incompetent husband upon me as well?
¿Y ahora también quieres endosarme un marido incompetente?
This will not go
Esto no va a suceder
as you wish, Father.
Como desees, Padre.
I won't let that happen.
No permitiré que eso suceda.
Nuptials?
¿Nupcias?
Did you agree to it?
¿Estuviste de acuerdo?
Maybe.
Tal vez.
You're really going to?
¿De verdad lo vas a hacer?
Why not?
¿Por qué no?
Since when did Your Royal Highness become so obedient?
¿Desde cuándo Su Alteza Real se ha vuelto tan obediente?
And since when have you grown so insolent?
¿Y desde cuándo te has vuelto tan insolente?
My apologies, sir.
Mis disculpas, señor.
I'm just frustrated with the situation, that's all.
Simplemente estoy frustrado con la situación, eso es todo.
I mean, all this time, she was firmly against your nuptials.
Es decir, durante todo este tiempo, ella se opuso firmemente a tu boda.
And now, she wants you to get married?
¿Y ahora quiere que te cases con ella?
To a woman she chooses, no less?
¿Y nada menos que a una mujer que ella misma elige?
This is downright unreasonable.
Esto es totalmente irrazonable.
Darn it.
Maldita sea.
We did this last year.
Lo hicimos el año pasado.
And this is what our competitor is doing.
Y esto es lo que está haciendo nuestro competidor.
Did you need more time or something?
¿Necesitabas más tiempo o algo así?
Ms. Seong, the thing about PR is--
Señorita Seong, lo que pasa con las relaciones públicas es...
Don't tell me there are only so many ways to spin it.
No me digas que solo hay un número limitado de maneras de darle la vuelta a la situación.
If that's your excuse, you should resign.
Si esa es tu excusa, deberías renunciar.
You're saying anyone could do your job.
Estás diciendo que cualquiera podría hacer tu trabajo.
If it's all the same, why carry a bloated payroll?
Si todo es igual, ¿por qué mantener una nómina tan abultada?
My apologies.
Mis disculpas.
We'll revise based on your feedback and get back to you, ma'am.
Revisaremos el proyecto en función de sus comentarios y nos pondremos en contacto con usted, señora.
Here we go.
Aquí vamos.
Drink some. It's lotus root tea.
Toma un poco. Es té de raíz de loto.
Isn't this super bitter?
¿No es esto súper amargo?
Come on. Just drink it.
Vamos. Solo bébelo.
It soothes pent-up anger.
Calma la ira reprimida.
I don't have any pent-up anger.
No tengo ninguna ira reprimida.
You've been riding the staff for days now.
Llevas días montando el bastón.
Listen, I know you're on edge with the marriage issue and all,
Escucha, sé que estás nervioso con el tema del matrimonio y todo eso,
but don't drag personal issues into the workplace.
pero no traslades tus problemas personales al lugar de trabajo.
-You look really petty. -What?
-Pareces muy mezquino. -¿Qué?
"Petty"?
"Insignificante"?
Who? Me?
¿Quién? ¿Yo?
Ms. Do. I am Seong Huiju!
Señora Do. ¡Soy Seong Huiju!
Yeah, sure. Here.
Sí, claro. Toma.
Go on.
Seguir.
Drink it.
Bébelo.
So bitter.
Qué amargo.
Your Royal Highness.
Su Alteza Real.
Lord INPYEONG.
Señor INPYEONG.
It appears you are leaving the palace.
Parece que estás abandonando el palacio.
Yes, I am taking some time off.
Sí, me tomaré un tiempo libre.
"Time off"?
¿"Tiempo libre"?
His Majesty's birthday preparations had me held up in the palace for a while.
Los preparativos del cumpleaños de Su Majestad me mantuvieron retenido en el palacio durante un tiempo.
I intend to spend a few days resting at my private residence.
Tengo intención de pasar unos días descansando en mi residencia privada.
Your private residence?
¿Su residencia privada?
Then who will safeguard the palace, Your Royal Highness?
¿Quién, entonces, protegerá el palacio, Su Alteza Real?
What would we do if you were to leave the palace alone
¿Qué haríamos si dejaras el palacio solo?
and misfortune befell you?
¿Y te sobrevino la desgracia?
I thought you would welcome my absence.
Pensé que agradecerías mi ausencia.
Perhaps I was under the wrong impression.
Quizás tenía una impresión equivocada.
Please give my best to Queen Mother.
Por favor, dale mis saludos a la Reina Madre.
I was so excited about my time off that I forgot to pay my respects.
Estaba tan emocionado por mis vacaciones que me olvidé de presentar mis respetos.
Is that what you said to him?
¿Eso fue lo que le dijiste?
It was His Majesty's royal birthday.
Era el cumpleaños real de Su Majestad.
He showed up late…
Llegó tarde…
wearing a cheollik.
vistiendo un cheollik.
A fire even broke out.
Incluso se produjo un incendio.
That was all I-AN--
Eso fue todo, I-AN--
Your Majesty.
Su Majestad.
And the members of the royal family?
¿Y los miembros de la familia real?
Despite tirelessly preaching propriety, they do not dare utter
A pesar de predicar incansablemente la decencia, no se atreven a decir
a single word of remonstrance before the Grand Prince.
una sola palabra de protesta ante el Gran Príncipe.
The people cherish the Grand Prince.
El pueblo venera al Gran Príncipe.
Even after losing his parents and brother,
Incluso después de perder a sus padres y a su hermano,
he continues to serve as regent for his nephew,
continúa ejerciendo como regente de su sobrino,
safeguarding the Crown.
salvaguardar la Corona.
That is precisely the issue.
Ese es precisamente el problema.
His Majesty is but a child, throwing the disparity
Su Majestad no es más que un niño, arrojando la disparidad
between him and the Grand Prince behind him into even starker relief.
Entre él y el Gran Príncipe que estaba detrás, la línea divisoria se hacía aún más evidente.
KIM YEONGHUN, CEO OF SEONGSAN TEXTILE
KIM YEONGHUN, DIRECTOR EJECUTIVO DE SEONGSAN TEXTILE
None of them?
¿Ninguno de ellos?
Come on.
Vamos.
How are they any different from the men Father picked?
¿En qué se diferencian de los hombres que mi padre eligió?
At least be handsome if you're a lost cause in the corporate rankings.
Al menos sé guapo si eres un caso perdido en los rankings corporativos.
No money.
Sin dinero.
No looks to speak of.
No tiene aspecto destacable.
Tsk, tsk, tsk.
Tsk, tsk, tsk.
What about politicians? No candidates there?
¿Y los políticos? ¿No hay candidatos?
Why is it all businessmen?
¿Por qué son todos hombres de negocios?
Politicians don't like mixing with business people.
A los políticos no les gusta relacionarse con la gente de negocios.
They love money but hate business people?
¿Les encanta el dinero pero odian a los empresarios?
Too much potential baggage.
Demasiada carga potencial.
-Illegal succession, tax evasion… -What?
-Sucesión ilegal, evasión fiscal… -¿Qué?
That's ridiculous.
Eso es ridículo.
Either way, politicians are a no-go.
En cualquier caso, los políticos son un tema tabú.
They traditionally prefer aristocrats.
Tradicionalmente, prefieren a los aristócratas.
Aristocrats? You must be kidding.
¿Aristócratas? ¡Debes estar bromeando!
Are we living in the Joseon era? Are they trying to marry up?
¿Estamos viviendo en la era Joseon? ¿ Están intentando casarse con alguien de mayor estatus social?
That's not something for you to say.
Eso no es algo que te corresponda decir.
Ms. Do. Come on, Ms. Do!
Señorita Do. ¡Vamos, señorita Do!
I'm simply looking for someone who matches my current status. That's all.
Simplemente busco a alguien que se ajuste a mi situación actual. Eso es todo.
He doesn't need to be super impressive.
No necesita ser súper impresionante.
Just someone of my capability,
Solo alguien de mi capacidad,
my means, and my beauty.
mis recursos y mi belleza.
Is that too much to ask?
¿Es mucho pedir?
It's not like I'm looking to marry into the royal…
No es que esté buscando casarme con alguien de la realeza…
family.
familia.
Huh…
Eh…
Didn't I warn you?
¿No te lo advertí?
Just look at this.
Solo mira esto.
I-AN, THE 21ST-CENTURY PRINCE SUYANG
I-AN, EL PRÍNCIPE SUYANG DEL SIGLO XXI
This is no time for doodling orchids.
No es momento para dibujar orquídeas.
I told you wearing the cheollik was a bad idea.
Ya te dije que usar el cheollik era una mala idea.
Didn't I beg you to wear proper court attire?
¿Acaso no te rogué que vistieras de forma apropiada para la corte?
The Royal Secretariat and Public Affairs Office
La Secretaría Real y la Oficina de Asuntos Públicos
are outraged right now.
están indignados ahora mismo.
-And the public? -They're in an uproar.
-¿Y el público? -Están indignados.
Is there any mention of the fire?
¿Se menciona el incendio en algún momento?
Pardon?
¿Indulto?
It appears my nickname
Parece que mi apodo
will be trending once more.
volverá a ser tendencia.
The regent Grand Prince I-AN has recently come under public scrutiny.
El regente, el Gran Príncipe I-AN, ha sido objeto de escrutinio público recientemente.
Good morning.
Buen día.
Ms. Do, look at this.
Señora Do, mire esto.
The controversy stems from his appearance.
La controversia surge de su apariencia.
-As the cheollik is considered informal… -Amazing, no?
-Como el cheollik se considera informal… -Increíble, ¿verdad?
…many viewed it as inappropriate for a Grand Prince at a royal celebration.
…muchos lo consideraron inapropiado para un Gran Príncipe en una celebración real.
He looks so sharp in that.
Se ve muy elegante con eso.
Members of the royal family have voiced criticism.
Miembros de la familia real han expresado sus críticas.
They argue that preserving tradition and decorum is the duty of the crown,
Argumentan que preservar la tradición y el decoro es deber de la corona,
and that the Grand Prince's recent bizarre behavior is unacceptable.
y que el comportamiento extraño y reciente del Gran Príncipe es inaceptable.
"Bizarre"? That's taking it too far.
¿"Extraño"? Eso es exagerar.
It's not like he was carrying a sword.
No es que llevara una espada.
Political circles praised him for putting practicality ahead of protocol
Los círculos políticos lo elogiaron por anteponer la practicidad al protocolo.
and modeling a modern monarchy.
y modelando una monarquía moderna.
Politicians always take Grand Prince I-AN's side.
Los políticos siempre se ponen del lado del Gran Príncipe I-AN.
Why?
¿Por qué?
Because the people are enamored with the Grand Prince.
Porque el pueblo está enamorado del Gran Príncipe.
-He's so cool. -Let's get back to work.
-Es genial. -Volvamos al trabajo.
PRINCE I-AN IN CHEOLLIK AT ROYAL BIRTHDAY BANQUET
EL PRÍNCIPE I-AN CON CHEOLLIK EN EL BANQUETE REAL DE CUMPLEAÑOS
Ah. His hype is next-level.
Ah. Su popularidad es de otro nivel.
-What? -Grand Prince I-AN.
-¿Qué? -Gran Príncipe I-AN.
Right.
Bien.
The executive operations team is buzzing about it.
El equipo de operaciones ejecutivas está entusiasmado con ello.
Really?
¿En realidad?
What do you think of him?
¿Qué opinas de él?
PRINCE I-AN IN CHEOLLIK AT ROYAL BIRTHDAY BANQUET
EL PRÍNCIPE I-AN CON CHEOLLIK EN EL BANQUETE REAL DE CUMPLEAÑOS
I think…
Creo…
he's quite nice.
Es bastante simpático.
What?
¿Qué?
You told me not to pick them.
Me dijiste que no los eligiera.
Well, I mean,
Bueno, quiero decir,
you mentioned that arranging flowers can quiet a restless mind.
Mencionaste que arreglar flores puede calmar una mente inquieta.
Why on earth are you remaining silent? You should defend yourself.
¿Por qué diablos permaneces en silencio? Deberías defenderte.
Of course, it is true that you violated decorum.
Por supuesto, es cierto que usted violó el decoro.
Proper court attire was a must.
Era imprescindible ir vestido de forma apropiada para la corte.
But what can we do?
Pero, ¿qué podemos hacer?
You remain so enamored with the spotlight.
Sigues tan fascinado con ser el centro de atención.
But is that such a crime?
Pero, ¿eso constituye un delito?
Is it so wrong to want some attention in the 21st century?
¿Acaso está mal querer llamar la atención en el siglo XXI?
Let's be real. Court attire isn't the most flattering.
Seamos realistas. La vestimenta para ir a la cancha no es la más favorecedora.
The cheollik is so much cooler, isn't it?
El cheollik es mucho más genial, ¿verdad?
For one thing, court attire has such a drab palette.
Para empezar, la indumentaria de la corte tiene una paleta de colores muy apagada.
Such a grim brown.
Un marrón tan sombrío.
Sure, it might suit someone like me
Claro, podría quedarle bien a alguien como yo.
with a warm, golden complexion.
con una tez cálida y dorada.
I can pull off colors like that just fine.
Puedo usar esos colores sin problema.
But on someone like Your Royal Highness, with that icy cool tone,
Pero en alguien como Su Alteza Real, con ese tono gélido y frío,
it would just clash.
it would just clash.
Give me a break already.
Give me a break already.
-That's enough. -"That's enough."
-That's enough. -"That's enough."
-Tell them. -Tell them what?
-Tell them. -Tell them what?
You meant no dishonor to His Majesty,
You meant no dishonor to His Majesty,
and you were only expressing your simple, unassuming taste.
and you were only expressing your simple, unassuming taste.
Just issue that statement already.
Just issue that statement already.
"Prince Suyang of the 21st-century"?
"Prince Suyang of the 21st-century"?
How does that make any sense?
How does that make any sense?
Why not?
Why not?
You can't.
You can't.
-Why not? -Of course, you can't.
-Why not? -Of course, you can't.
Right.
Right.
And why is that exactly?
And why is that exactly?
Are you drunk?
Are you drunk?
No.
No.
Then what has gotten into you?
Then what has gotten into you?
How can you even think about marrying Prince I-AN?
How can you even think about marrying Prince I-AN?
Ms. Do, just think about it.
Ms. Do, just think about it.
How many are as beautiful,
How many are as beautiful,
as intelligent,
as intelligent,
and as wealthy as I am?
and as wealthy as I am?
Where else could you find such a match in this world?
Where else could you find such a match in this world?
Okay.
Okay.
No one else knows, right?
No one else knows, right?
-You didn't tell anyone else, right? -You're the first.
-You didn't tell anyone else, right? -You're the first.
Good thinking.
Good thinking.
But I did submit a request for a royal audience.
But I did submit a request for a royal audience.
What? A royal audience request?
What? A royal audience request?
Where? How?
Where? How?
Royal audience requests?
Royal audience requests?
I guess you really are trending.
I guess you really are trending.
The Prime Minister's Office reached out.
The Prime Minister's Office reached out.
Lord Jeongseon is begging for a meeting too.
Lord Jeongseon is begging for a meeting too.
Lord Jeongseon too?
Lord Jeongseon too?
He must be itching to chime in. You know how talkative he is.
He must be itching to chime in. You know how talkative he is.
So nosy.
So nosy.
Oh, right!
Oh, right!
Ms. Seong Huiju has also submitted a request. How shall I proceed?
Ms. Seong Huiju has also submitted a request. How shall I proceed?
-Seong Huiju? -Yes, the CEO of Castle Beauty.
-Seong Huiju? -Yes, the CEO of Castle Beauty.
The illegitimate-born of Castle Group.
The illegitimate-born of Castle Group.
YOUR AUDIENCE REQUEST HAS BEEN REJECTED
YOUR AUDIENCE REQUEST HAS BEEN REJECTED
Why was it rejected? I haven't said a word yet.
Why was it rejected? I haven't said a word yet.
It's okay, Ms. Seong.
It's okay, Ms. Seong.
An audience with Prince I-AN is no easy feat.
An audience with Prince I-AN is no easy feat.
And I'm easy?
And I'm easy?
I'm an incredibly busy person too.
I'm an incredibly busy person too.
Prince I-AN is currently a regent.
Prince I-AN is currently a regent.
He's basically the king.
He's basically the king.
Plus, you said you didn't even write a reason for the request.
Plus, you said you didn't even write a reason for the request.
What kind of king would give up his time for someone like that?
What kind of king would give up his time for someone like that?
Then what should I do?
Then what should I do?
Should I have written, "I wish to marry you"?
Should I have written, "I wish to marry you"?
Stop talking about that damn marriage, okay?
Stop talking about that damn marriage, okay?
I feel like I'm about to get arrested any minute.
I feel like I'm about to get arrested any minute.
Hold on.
Hold on.
No way.
No way.
Is he playing hard to get?
Is he playing hard to get?
He totally is.
He totally is.
Have we not heard from Grand Prince I-AN?
Have we not heard from Grand Prince I-AN?
No, both the Royal Secretariat
No, both the Royal Secretariat
and Lord Jeongseon are pressing him on the matter.
and Lord Jeongseon are pressing him on the matter.
But he has even turned down Prime Minister Min's audience request.
But he has even turned down Prime Minister Min's audience request.
Is this his way of saying he remains completely unfazed?
Is this his way of saying he remains completely unfazed?
You're practically climbing into that book at this rate.
You're practically climbing into that book at this rate.
Why did you ask for this food?
Why did you ask for this food?
Did I do something wrong?
Did I do something wrong?
You eat it.
You eat it.
Seriously?
Seriously?
I didn't know you cared for me so much.
I didn't know you cared for me so much.
Thank you for the food.
Thank you for the food.
Mmm.
Mmm.
Yes, eat that and stop talking.
Sí, cómetelo y deja de hablar.
Huh?
¿Eh?
All your nagging
Todas tus quejas
is drowning out the sound of rain.
está ahogando el sonido de la lluvia.
Yes, sir.
Sí, señor.
But this is important…
Pero esto es importante…
Ms. Seong has submitted another request for a royal audience.
La Sra. Seong ha presentado otra solicitud para una audiencia real.
How shall I respond this time?
¿Cómo debo responder esta vez?
-Again? -Yes.
-¿Otra vez? -Sí.
I rejected it due to scheduling conflicts.
Lo rechacé debido a problemas de agenda.
But she submitted another request right away.
Pero ella presentó otra solicitud de inmediato.
With a different name, no less.
Y con otro nombre, nada menos.
What does that mean?
¿Qué significa eso?
The first request clearly stated, "Seong Huiju from Castle Beauty."
La primera solicitud decía claramente: "Seong Huiju de Castle Beauty".
This time, she put, "Castle Group Seong Hyeonguk's second daughter."
Esta vez, escribió: " La segunda hija de Seong Hyeonguk, del Grupo Castle".
Reject it.
Recházalo.
YOUR AUDIENCE REQUEST HAS BEEN REJECTED
SU SOLICITUD DE AUDIENCIA HA SIDO RECHAZADA
Again?
¿De nuevo?
Is he trying to get me riled up?
¿Está intentando provocarme?
Unbelievable.
Increíble.
Have some.
Toma un poco.
We all work to fill our bellies, don't we?
Todos trabajamos para llenar nuestros estómagos, ¿verdad?
Go on.
Seguir.
What's this?
¿Qué es esto?
-It's delicious. -Good, right?
-Está delicioso. -¿Verdad que sí?
It just opened across the street.
Acaba de abrir al otro lado de la calle.
The whole team orders from there frequently.
Todo el equipo hace pedidos de allí con frecuencia.
Hey.
Ey.
Tell them to share the treats they find instead of just gorging themselves!
¡Dígales que compartan las golosinas que encuentren en lugar de atiborrarse ellos solos!
It'd be best if we didn't have to work so late.
Lo mejor sería que no tuviéramos que trabajar hasta tan tarde.
God, this is beyond infuriating.
Dios, esto es exasperante.
So what if he's a grand prince?
¿Y qué si es un gran príncipe?
Maybe it's because I didn't put down a reason?
¿Tal vez sea porque no puse una razón?
ROYAL AUDIENCE REQUEST
PETICIÓN DEL PÚBLICO REAL
Your Royal Highness,
Su Alteza Real,
Castle Group, under the benevolent care of the Crown,
Grupo de castillos, bajo el benévolo cuidado de la Corona,
has continued to achieve remarkable growth and development,
ha continuado logrando un crecimiento y desarrollo notables,
attaining the honor of being the top conglomerate…
alcanzar el honor de ser el principal conglomerado…
Ah, is this a bit too much?
Ah, ¿esto es demasiado?
I sincerely pledge to further the nation's development,
Me comprometo sinceramente a impulsar el desarrollo de la nación,
and I hereby request an audience.
Y por la presente solicito una audiencia.
I patiently await the sagacious counsel
Espero pacientemente el sabio consejo.
of Your Royal Highness.
de Su Alteza Real.
"Executive Director of Castle Group,
"Director Ejecutivo de Castle Group,
Seong Huiju."
Seong Huiju.
SUBMIT
ENTREGAR
YOUR REQUEST HAS BEEN SUBMITTED
SU SOLICITUD HA SIDO ENVIADA
Ha!
Ha!
Seriously, what's gotten into her?
En serio, ¿qué le pasa?
Your Royal Highness, Ms. Seong…
Su Alteza Real, la Sra. Seong…
-Reject it. -Yes, sir.
-Rechácelo. -Sí, señor.
-Your Royal Highness. -Reject it.
-Su Alteza Real. -Rechácelo.
Yes, sir.
Sí, señor.
-Yes, sir.
-Sí, señor.
Got it.
Entiendo.
Ms. Seong--
Sra. Seong--
-Reject it! -Yes, sir!
-¡Recházalo! -¡Sí, señor!
Ms. Seong continues to submit her requests.
La Sra. Seong continúa presentando sus solicitudes.
How much longer must I…
¿Cuánto tiempo más debo...?
REJECT IT
RECHAZARLO
-Your Royal Highness. -Reject it.
-Su Alteza Real. -Rechácelo.
But wait--
Pero espera...
-Reject it! -Rejected.
-¡Recházalo! -Rechazado.
I reject your request for an audience.
Rechazo su solicitud de audiencia.
Oh, my goodness.
Oh Dios mío.
Jeez, what's wrong with her?
Dios mío, ¿qué le pasa?
If you're gone in the count of three, I'll overlook it.
Si te vas en tres segundos, lo pasaré por alto.
Really?
¿En realidad?
That much I can do for my junior alum.
Eso es todo lo que puedo hacer por mis compañeros exalumnos.
She has already submitted over five requests.
Ella ya ha presentado más de cinco solicitudes.
With another new name this time?
¿Con un nombre nuevo esta vez?
Yes, she put down "Junior alum" this time.
Sí, esta vez puso "Exalumno de segundo año".
-"Junior alum"? -Yes.
-¿Exalumno de tercer año? -Sí.
She requests the esteemed counsel of her senior alum this time.
En esta ocasión , solicita el valioso consejo de su exalumna de último año.
What's this now? Are you two alumni?
¿Qué es esto? ¿Ustedes dos son exalumnos?
I assume it's another rejection?
Supongo que es otro rechazo, ¿no?
Grant it.
Concédelo.
Pardon?
¿Indulto?
How can I say no
¿Cómo puedo decir que no?
to a junior alum in need?
¿A un exalumno de segundo año que lo necesite?
YOUR AUDIENCE REQUEST HAS BEEN ACCEPTED
SU PETICIÓN DE AUDIENCIA HA SIDO ACEPTADA
It worked.
Funcionó.
Who did you say was there?
¿Quién dijiste que estaba allí?
Executive Director Seong Huiju of Castle Group.
Seong Huiju, Director Ejecutivo de Castle Group.
You said you had a mole planted at his residence, right?
Dijiste que tenías un informante infiltrado en su residencia, ¿verdad?
-Yes, Your Majesty. -Can I trust her?
—Sí, Su Majestad. —¿Puedo confiar en ella?
Yes. You may call upon her at any time.
Sí. Puedes acudir a ella en cualquier momento.
I am not sure what to call you.
No estoy seguro de cómo llamarte.
You seem to go by many names.
Parece que te conocen por muchos nombres.
I was not sure which one you would prefer.
No estaba seguro de cuál preferirías.
Why did you seek me so earnestly?
¿Por qué me buscabas con tanto ahínco?
I wanted to propose.
Quería proponerle matrimonio.
Let's…
Vamos…
get married.
casarse.
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA
Let's…
Vamos…
get married.
casarse.
My pedigree is impressive, and my acumen sharper still.
Mi pedigrí es impresionante, y mi perspicacia aún más.
I decline.
Me niego.
I was rejected.
Me rechazaron.
-I missed you. -Seong Huiju?
-Te extrañé. -¿Seong Huiju?
Hyah!
¡Hyah!
You dared to run a background check on me?
¿Te atreviste a hacerme una verificación de antecedentes?
-Yes. -"Yes"?
—Sí. —¿"Sí"?
I must meet this maiden.
Debo encontrarme con esta doncella.
"Grand Prince I-AN's secret lover"?
¿"La amante secreta del Gran Príncipe I-AN"?
Me?
¿A mí?
-They're even speculating you're pregnant. -What?
-Incluso están especulando que estás embarazada. -¿Qué?
You would marry me for nothing more than a hollow title?
¿Te casarías conmigo solo por un título vacío?
EPILOGUE
EPÍLOGO
And considering how easily you secured this approval,
Y teniendo en cuenta la facilidad con la que obtuviste esta aprobación,
I guess it was only out of reach for me.
Supongo que solo estaba fuera de mi alcance.
So do not lecture me about demerit points or whatever.
Así que no me des lecciones sobre puntos de penalización ni nada por el estilo.
I'm so screwed.
Estoy jodido.
Am I going to get expelled?
¿Me van a expulsar?
What if I end up in prison for insulting the royal family?
¿Qué pasaría si acabara en prisión por insultar a la familia real?
Why on earth did I do that?
¿Por qué demonios hice eso?
Hey, get up.
Oye, levántate.
Hurry, get up. There's an announcement.
¡Rápido, levántate! Hay un anuncio.
What announcement?
¿Qué anuncio?
Get up. Hurry.
Levántate. Date prisa.
It's total chaos. Everyone's freaking out.
Es un caos total. Todo el mundo está histérico.
Why?
¿Por qué?
As Confucius said,
Como dijo Confucio,
"Though a noble man does not contend with others,
"Aunque un hombre noble no compite con los demás,
he must compete when it comes to archery."
Debe competir en lo que respecta al tiro con arco.
The forthcoming exhibition match
El próximo partido de exhibición
celebrates that spirit.
celebra ese espíritu.
Thus, students shall devote themselves to their training.
Por lo tanto, los estudiantes deberán dedicarse a su formación.
Well? Isn't this amazing?
¿Y bien? ¿No es esto asombroso?
The range will be open for a whole month.
El campo de tiro estará abierto durante todo un mes.
You said you didn't have enough time to train.
Dijiste que no tenías suficiente tiempo para entrenar.
The sole condition for access
La única condición para el acceso
shall be the observance
será la observancia
of protocol and decorum.
de protocolo y decoro.
Translated by Justin S. Kim
Traducido por Justin S. Kim
PERFECT CROWN
CORONA PERFECTA